Michael Sachs

www.mikesachs.com mike@mikesachs.com am a data scientist, physicist and designer who is interested in the stories data can tell. I have led teams, been part of technology start-ups, and consulted with companies both large and small. My work has been published in scientific journals, covered by the popular science press, and I have given talks at scientific conferences in Hawaii, Singapore, San Francisco, Santa Fe and New York. I studied physics at Columbia University and the University of California, Davis, and visual design at Virginia Commonwealth University. I am a NASA Earth and Space Science fellow and a Santa Fe Institute Complex Systems Summer School alumni, and most recently, the head of Product at FLYR in San Francisco.

Technologies

Languages

Python and SQL are my languages of choice. I've worked with: JavaScript, C, C++, HTML, CSS, Java, php, CQL, bash shell scripting, Objective C, IDL, Mathematica, MatLab, lisp, and ActionScript.

Applications, Modules, Libraries and Frameworks

My most recent experience is with: Spark, Databricks, Numpy, Scikit-learn, TensorFlow/Keras, Scipy, Pandas, MySQL/PostgreSQL, Google BigQuery, Matplotlib, Jira, and Confluence. In the past I have used: SQLAlchemy, Celery, Cassandra, Redshift, D3.js, Boto, Flask, HDF5, Django, JQuery, PIL, Ajax, Hadoop, WordPress, MPI, Mathematica, HEALPix, GeoFEST, LaGriT, Polspice, Adobe Illustrator, and Adobe Photoshop.

Cloud Platforms

Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform

Professional Experience

FLYR

Head of Product, Head of ML Ops November 2018 to April 2020

FLYR is using AI to change how airlines price tickets. I was hired to lead the creation of end-to-end ML development tools to speed the iteration and deployment of new models. Later I was tapped to lead product development for the whole company. My team and I helped FLYR scale their product to multiple airlines, build better model evaluation techniques and introduce more robust model architectures. We also managed relationships with FLYRs airline partners including Jetblue, AirAsia and Air New Zealand.

Creative Director/Lead Designer

March 1997 to June 2002

- Designed and implemented user interface strategies for over 30 companies in market sectors ranging from healthcare and education to broadband and packaged consumer goods.
- Led an award-winning team of designers and user interface engineers through mentoring, selective hiring, and the development of management systems.
- Guided the development of Xperts software design methodology in collaboration with other company executives.
- Facilitated the acquisition of new business by developing sales strategies, project estimates and bid presentations.
- Directed the organizational wide acceptance of new user interface and design technologies.

Creative Director/Lead Designer

March 1997 to lune 2002

- Designed and implemented user interface strategies for over 30 companies in market sectors ranging from healthcare and education to broadband and packaged consumer goods.
- Led an award-winning team of designers and user interface engineers through mentoring, selective hiring, and the development of management systems.

1

Radius Intelligence

Delivering B2B marketing data backed by The Network of Record, the most comprehensive, accurate and up-to date directory of businesses in the United States. Backed by Founders Fund and American Express Ventures.

Discovery Digital Networks

Creating original short form digital video content on topics ranging from technology to philosophy. A division of Discovery Communications.

Department of Physics, University of California, Davis

Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Columbia University

Mikesachs.com

Weill Cornell Medical College/NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital

Xperts Inc.

Letterbrain.com

Education

University of California, Davis
Columbia University
Virginia Commonwealth University

Publications

Parametrizing Physics-Based Earthquake Simulations

K. W. Schultz, M. R. Yoder, J. M. Wilson, E. M. Heien, **M. K. Sachs**, J. B. Rundle, and D. L. Turcotte Pure and Applied Geophysics(2016)

Virtual Quake: Statistics, Co-Seismic Deformations and Gravity Changes for Driven Earthquake Fault Systems

K. W. Schultz, **M. K. Sachs**, E. M. Heien, M. R. Yoder, J. B. Rundle, D. L. Turcotte, and A. Donnellan International Symposium on Geodesy for Earthquake and Natural Hazards (GENAH)14529-37(2015)

Simulating Gravity Changes in Topologically Realistic Driven Earthquake Fault Systems: First Results K. W. Schultz, **M. K. Sachs**, E. M. Heien, J. B. Rundle, D. L. Turcotte, and A. Donnellan Pure and Applied GeophysicsIn press(2014)

Self-Organizing Complex Earthquakes: Scaling in Data, Models, and Forecasting M. K. Sachs , J. B. Rundle, J. R. Holliday, J. Gran, M. Yoder and W. Graves "Self-Organized Criticality Systems" Open Academic Press (2013)

A Comparison among Observations and Earthquake Simulator Results for the allcal2 California Fault Model

T. E. Tullis, K. Richards-Dinger, M. Barall, J. H. Dieterich, E. H. Field, E. M. Heien, L. H. Kellogg, F. Pollitz, J. B. Rundle, **M. K. Sachs**, D. L. Turcotte, S. N. Ward and M. B. Yikilmaz Seismological Research Letters

Generic Earthquake Simulator

T. E. Tullis, K. Richards-Dinger, M. Barall, J. H. Dieterich, E. H. Field, E. M. Heien, L. H. Kellogg, F. Pollitz,

J. B. Rundle, **M. K. Sachs**, D. L. Turcotte, S. N. Ward and M. B. Yikilmaz Seismological Research Letters83959-963(2012)

Virtual California Earthquake Simulator

M. K. Sachs , E. M. Heien, D. L. Turcotte, M. B. Yikilmaz, J. B. Rundle and L. H. Kellogg Seismological Research Letters83973-978(2012)

Forecasting Earthquakes: The RELM Test

M. K. Sachs , D. L. Turcotte, J. R. Holliday and J. B. Rundle Computing in Science and Engineering 1443 (2012)

Understanding Long-Term Earthquake Behavior through Simulation

E. M. Heien and M. K. Sachs

Computing in Science and Engineering 1410(2012)

Black swans, power laws, and dragon-kings: Earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, landslides, wildfires, floods, and SOC models

M. K. Sachs, M. R. Yoder, D. L. Turcotte, J. B. Rundle and B. D. Malamud European Physical Journal Special Topics205167-182(2012)

Implications of the RELM test of earthquake forecasts in California

M. K. Sachs, Y. T. Lee, D. L. Turcotte, J. R. Holliday and J. B. Rundle Research in Geophysics2e10(2012)

Evaluating the RELM test results

M. K. Sachs, Y. T. Lee, D. L. Turcotte, J. R. Holliday and J. B. Rundle International Journal of Geophysics2012(2012)

Earthquake precursors: activation or quiescence?

J. B. Rundle, J. R. Holliday, M. Yoder, **M. K. Sachs** , A. Donnellan, D. L. Turcotte, K. F. Tiampo, W. Klein and L. H. Kellogg

Geophysical Journal International 187225-236 (2011)

Results of the Regional Earthquake Likelihood Models (RELM) test of earthquake forecasts in California

Y. T. Lee, D. L. Turcotte, J. R. Holliday, **M. K. Sachs** , J. B. Rundle, C. C. Chen and K. F. Tiampo Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (USA)10816533-16538(2011)

Testing Lattice Quantum Gravity in 2+1 Dimensions

M. K. Sachs

arXiv:1110.6880 [gr-qc](2011)

Awards and Recognition

Conferences

AGU 2013

AGU 2012

EcoSummit 2012

AOGS 2012

AGU 2011

SCEC 2011

ACES 2011

Teaching Experience

Department of Physics, University of California, Davis

Press

scientificamerican.com

Test Pits Earthquake Forecasts against Each Other :

http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=test-pits-earthquake-forecasts

msnbc.com

Flagging quake hotspots an inexact science:

http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/44676488/ns/technology_and_science-science/#.TrB2c2B8tjB

UCDavis News

Assessing California earthquake forecasts:

http://www.news.ucdavis.edu/search/news_detail.lasso?id=10025

NASA

Managing the Deluge of 'Big Data' From Space :

http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.php?release=2013-299

QuakeSim and NASA Mobile App Win NASA Software Award:

http://www.nasa.gov/topics/earth/features/quakesim20120920.html